Guide to the James Jackson Jarves Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
James Jackson Jarves collection
1838-1954
MS 301
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
6.5
(7 boxes)
Consists of family correspondence, general correspondence, diaries, and memorabilia of the Jarves family. Major family correspondents are James Jackson Jarves, his first wife, Elizabeth Russell Swain Jarves, his son Horatio Deming Jarves, and his second wife Isabel Heyden Jarves. Collection also contains working files of Francis Steegmuller, author of The Two Lives of James Jackson Jarves, 1951.
Jarves, James Jackson, 1818-1888
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Francis Steegmuller, Flora Amey Jarves, and Theodore Sizer.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series: I. Correspondence. II. Special Files. III. Working Files for The Two Lives of James Jackson Jarves by Francis Steegmuller
Scope and Contents
The James Jackson Jarves Collection consist primarily of correspondence, which has been divided into three subsections: "Family Correspondence", "General Correspondence," and "Correspondence of Others". In "Family Correspondence" either the author and/or recipient of each letter is a family member. The entire subsection consists of 26 folders and is arranged alphabetically by author. The letters written by the ten authors in this section include those of James Jackson Jarves to his children; Elizabeth Russell Swain Jarves (first wife of Jarves) to her own parents (Mr. and Mrs. Oliver Swain); and Isabel Hayden Jarves (second wife of Jarves) to her stepchildren. Many of these letters give an insight into the often unhappy relationship between Jarves and other family members.
The 19 folders of "General Correspondence" are arranged alphabetically by author and contain letters dealing with Jarves' business and governmental activities in Hawaii. His inclination to provoke controversy is indicated by a series of heated exchanges between himself and J. Dudoit, French ambassador to Hawaii.
The last eight folders of correspondence consists of the "Correspondence of Others". These contain miscellaneous letters, some of which pertain to the Jarves art collection owned by Yale University.
The correspondence is followed by a few miscellaneous items, one including a diary by Elizabeth R. S. Jarves which renders her impressions about her first trip to Hawaii. Another diary, by Horatio Deming Jarves (James and Elizabeth Jarves' first child), records his account of his first few months of battle (1861) in the Civil War.
Boxes 2-5 contain the working files for Francis Steegmuller's The Two Lives of James Jackson Jarves (Yale University Press, 1951). These files include a large number of photostatic and transcript copies of letters of James Jackson Jarves and members of his family, plus photostatic copies of his writings and other related materials. The photostatic letters are copies of originals in the National Archives; the transcripts are copies of letters in Box 1, Series I. Also included are letters of Francis Steegmuller regarding research and publication of the book.
The Steegmuller addition was donated to Yale University by Mr. Steegmuller in 1955. It was added to the James Jackson Jarves Papers in 1980.
Biographical / Historical
James Jackson Jarves was born Aug. 20, 1818, the son of Deming Jarves, founder of the famous Sandwich Glass Co., and Anna Smith (Stutson) Jarves. After his early education at Chauncey Hall school, Boston, Mass., he planned to continue studies at Harvard University. Because of failing eye sight however, he was unable to attend. In search of a better climate for his health, Jarves sailed for Hawaii in 1837. He stayed in Hawaii until 1848 except for two brief interludes, one in 1838 when he returned to Boston to marry his first wife, Elizabeth Russell Swain; and the second in 1842 when the Jarves family returned to Boston after a silk worm industry in Hawaii, in which Jarves held a partnership, went bankrupt.
Although Jarves' business adventures in Hawaii were more often than not unsuccessful, he met with limited success as a writer and editor. In 1843 he wrote the History of the Hawaiian Islands, and in 1840 he established The Polynesian, one of the first Hawaiian newspapers to be written in English. In 1844 The Polynesian became the official governmental newspaper and Jarves, with a five year contract, received the title of Director of the Government Press.
An unhappy marriage caused Jarves to break with his wife in 1848, leave his governmental position, and return to America for three years where he again participated in a disastrous business adventure, this time involving land speculation in California.
In 1851 the Jarves' family (then reunited) settled in Florence, Italy, and there Jarves developed an interest in art - specifically in medieval Italian paintings. Using his father's income, he amassed a collection of paintings that, covering a period of 600 years, exhibited the progress of Italian painting from its early beginnings. As with his previous business endeavors, his art collection was never financially profitable for him. Jarves decided to sell his collection "en bloc" in America, but he could not find a buyer. After several unsuccessful attempts to sell his collection in Boston and New York City (1859-1866), he was finally able to display his collection at Yale College in 1867 for a loan of $20,000.00. Unable to repay the loan and $2,000.00 interest three years later, he was forced to auction his collection. It was sold to Yale for $22,000.00.
From the time that he settled in Florence until his death in 1888, Jarves' primary interest was art. Not only was he responsible for amassing a valuable European art collection and transporting it to the United States, but he was also a contributor to the art scholarship of the time. He wrote several books, including: Art Hints (1855); Art Studies: The Old Masters of Italy (1861); The Art Idea: Sculpture, Painting, and Architecture in America (1866); Art Thoughts: The Experiences and Observations of an American Amateur in Europe (1876).
For a more complete biography read: James Jackson Jarves, by Francis Steegmuller, Yale University Press, 1951.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Art -- Collectors and collecting; Art; Business; Families; Shipping; Asia; Hawaii -- Description and travel; Hawaii -- History -- To 1893; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Diaries; Kamehameha, King of the Hawaiian Islands, III, 1813-1854; Kamehameha, King of the Hawaiian Islands, IV, 1834-1863; Dudoit, J.; Jarves, Elizabeth Russell Swain; Jarves, Isabel Heyden; Jarves, James Jackson, 1818-1888; Steegmuller, Francis, 1906-1994; Wyllie, Robert Crichton, 1798-1865; Jarvis family
- Correspondence, 1838-1882, 1906-1908, 1954; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  The number of items are contained in parentheses before the unitdate
  - Family Correspondence
    - Anonymous
      - Jarves, Flora Amey (1), Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Jarves, Horatio Deming (1), Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Carmen R. Vida de Everett
      - Jarves, Elizabeth Russell Swain (1), 1851 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - [Chevalita Jarves]
      - [Jarves, Horatio Deming] (1), Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Chevalita Jarves
      - Jarves, James Jackson (1), Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Elizabeth Russell Swain Jarves
      - Jarves, Horatio Deming (12), 1848, 1849, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Swain, Maria L. (3), 1840, 1843, 1846 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Swain, Oliver (12), 1838-1841, [1845?] (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Swain, Oliver (12), 1846-1848, 1855,undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Swain, Mrs. Oliver (10), 1838, 1841, 1846, 1847, 1849, 1854, 1858 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Swain, Revilo (1), 1838 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Horatio Deming Jarves
      - "Aunty" (1), 1882 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Jarves, Chevalita (6), 1862, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Jarves, Elizabeth Russell Swain (1), [1860?] (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Isabel Hayden Jarves
      - Jarves, Flora Amey (14), 1863, 1864, 1866, 1868, 1870, 1875, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Jarves, Horatio Deming (6), 1874, 1875, 1882 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - James Jackson Jarves
      - Jarves, Chevalita (1), 1865 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Jarves, Flora Amey (19), 1863-1867 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Jarves, Flora Amey (20), 1868-1874 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - Jarves, Flora Amey (25), Undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - Jarves, Horatio Deming (13), 1857, 1871, 1872, 1874, 1875, 1876, 1882 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - Jarves, Horatio Deming (including letter fragments) (7), Undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - Swain, Oliver (3), 1839, 1840, 1841 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - Swain, Mrs. Oliver (3), 1841, 1850, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Mary W. Parker
      - Jarves, Flora Amey (1), Undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Maria L. Swain
      - Jarves, Elizabeth Russell Swain (1), 1857 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - General Correspondence
    - Ana, Keoni
      General
      See: box 1, folder 39
    - Black, Charles Christopher (1), [186?] (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Correnti, Cesare (1815-1888) (1), Undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Dudoit, J. (2), 1839 August (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Eastlake, Sir Charles Lock (1793-1865)(1), 1861 June 14 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Judd, G. P. (3), 1843, 1847, 1850 (Box 1, Folder 32)
      See Also: box 1, folder 44
    - Kamehameha III, King of Hawaii (?-1854) (1), 1841, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Kamehameha IV, King of Hawaii,(1854-1863) (1), 1858 March 26 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Kirkup, Seymour Stocker (1), 1859 October 6 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Mazzini, Giuseppe (1805-1872) (1), Undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Pasi, Raffaelli (1819-1890) (1), 1884 December 22 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Premier of Hawaii (1), 1847 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Richards, William (1), 1846 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - St. Julian, J. (1), 1848 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Stirling-Maxwell, Sir William (1), 1876 April 16 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Wyllie, R. C. (8), 1848 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Wyllie, R. C. (2), 1849 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Wyllie, R. C. (2), 1851 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Correspondence of Others
    - Anderson, Rufus (1790-1880)
      - [?] (1), 1851 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Bereusen, Mary
      - Weir, Prof. (1), 1908 January 31 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Jaccaci, August F.
      - Weir, Prof. (1), [1906?] November 30 (Box 1, Folder 48)
      - [?] (1), [1906?] December 10 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - G. P. Judd
      - Wylie, R. C.
        See: box 1, folder 44
    - Howard Kerr
      - Sizer, Theodore (1), 1954 June 22 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - J. C. Wyllie
      - Ricord, John (1), 1853 (Box 1, Folder 52)
- Special Files, Series II
  - Diary of Elizabeth Russell Swain Jarves (voyage to Hawaii) (1), 1838 November-December (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Diary of Horatio Deming Jarves (while soldier in Civil War) (1), 1861 April-October (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Expense list of glass furnished by E. Schwartz for pictures in Jarves Gallery (1), Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Obituaries, Jarves Family (3), Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Memorabilia - Jarves Family (5), Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Francis Steegmuller's notes of James J. Jarves' correspondence, Privy Council Records, and Minutes of Other Conferences. (3), 1846-1853 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Francis Steegmuller's notes on Privy Council Proceedings, 1847 August 5
- Working Files for The Two Lives of James Jackson Jarves by Francis Steegmuller, Series III
  - Correspondence of Francis Steegmuller re research and publication of The Two Lives of James Jackson Jarves, 1946-1950 (Box 2–3)
  - Author and subject files, [1946-1950?] (Box 3)
  - First draft of The Two Lives of James Jackson Jarves: typescript, Undated (Box 4)
  - Photostatic copies of letters and other materials from the National Archives re James Jackson Jarves, 1848-1882, undated (Box 4)
  - Photostatic copy of Descriptive Catalogue of "Old Masters" by James Jackson Jarves, 1860 (Box 4)
  - Transcripts of letters of James Jackson Jarves and members of his family, 1840-1861 (Box 4)
  - Photostatic copies of letters and writings and other materials re James Jackson Jarves, 1849-1882 (Box 5, Folder 1-4)
  - Photostatic copies of letters and writings and other materials re James Jackson Jarves, 1849-1882 (Box 5A, Folder 1-3)
  - Photostatic copies of letters and writings and other materials re James Jackson Jarves, 1849-1882 (Box 5B, Folder 1)
  - Photographs used in The Two Lives of James Jackson Jarves, Undated (Box 5B, Folder 2-3)